Guide to the Sally Provence Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sally Provence papers
1951-1991
MS 1660
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
33.75
The papers include correspondence and writings and research files which document the professional career of Sally Provence. Data from Provence's studies on child development comprise the bulk of the papers, which also include files from her involvement in the National Center for Clinical Infant Programs.
Provence, Sally, 1916-
Conditions Governing Access
Research data and patient case files in accession 2000-M-107 contain personal and senstitive information and are closed until January 1, 2086.
All other materials are open to research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Tim Provence, 1994; transfer from the Yale Child Study Center, 1996 and 2000.
Biographical / Historical
Sally Provence was born in East Texas in 1916. She completed her undergraduate work at Mary Hardin College and received her M.D. from Baylor Medical College. As a practicing pediatrician, Provence became interested in child development and, in 1949, she came to work in the Yale Child Study Center. In 1951 Provence founded the center's Child Development Unit, which she directed until her retirement in 1986. Her work included standards for children in institutions, studies of children in day care, and clinical intervention with multiply handicapped children. Appointed a Professor of Pediatrics at the Yale Child Study Center in 1967, she extended her teaching when, in 1978, she founded the National Center for Clinical Infant Programs. Sally Provence died in Branford, Connecticut on February 6, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence and writings and research files which document the professional career of Sally Provence. Data from Provence's studies on child development comprise the bulk of the papers, which also include files from her involvement in the National Center for Clinical Infant Programs.
Child care; Child development; Provence, Sally, 1916-; National Center for Clinical Infant Programs (U.S.); Yale University. Child Study Center
- Original accession, 1951-1991; Accession 1994-M-085; 7.5; (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Preliminary inventory by Diane E. Kaplan 1994 November
  Received from: Tim Provence, 1994 June 8
  - Correspondence and Subject Files
    - Allison, Bonnie, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - American Psychoanalytic Assoc. honorary membership, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Annual reports, 1951-1962, 1951-1968 (Box 1)
    - Assessment instrument (3 folders), 1979 (Box 1)
    - Assoc. for Child Psychoanalysis, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Autism Governor's Study, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Autism study, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Autistic follow-up ratings (SP & ML), 1977 (Box 1)
    - Axtmann, Annette, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Barnard, Kathyrn, undated (Box 1)
    - Basic Books, Inc, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Baylor College, 1981-1986 (Box 1)
    - Baylor Oral History Project, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Benedict, Helen, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Bloom-Feshbach, 1982-1987 (Box 1)
    - Brenneman, Judge F., 1982 (Box 1)
    - Chess, Stella, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Child analysis bibliography, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Child development bibliography, 1982-1983, undated (Box 1)
    - Child Study Center, 1975, 1963-1985 (Box 1)
    - Child Development Unit Programs, undated (Box 1)
    - Child Development Unit description, undated (Box 1)
    - Child Development Unit new unit, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Child Study Center Associates, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
    - Children's Clinical Research Center-Yale, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    - Classification, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Clinical Infants Centers Project, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Commonwealth Fund proposal, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
    - Connecticut Civil Liberties Foundation, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous, Circa 1978-1987 (Box 1)
    - Course of Life, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Daycare book, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Dees, Carmen Sue, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Developmental screening, undated (Box 1)
    - Emde, Robert, 1984, undated (Box 1)
    - Family Resource Coalition, 1983, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Fels Parent Behavior Scale, undated (Box 1)
    - Foley, Gilbert M., 1981-1986 (Box 1)
    - Forms--Child Welfare Research, 1970, 1978, undated (Box 1)
    - Forms, etc., 1969, undated (Box 1)
    - Forms for recording data, 1973, undated (Box 1)
    - Freud, Anna, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Gardiner, Emily A., 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Gershenson, Charles, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Gesell: How a Baby Grows, undated (Box 1)
    - Gesell Institute, 1983, undated (Box 1)
    - Goldstein, Joseph, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
    - Green, Morris, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Greenspan, Stanley, 1977-1985 (Box 1)
    - Goodfriend, Marlene, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Grover Powers Clinic, 1963-1973 (Box 1)
    - HCEEP/DEC Early Childhood Conference, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Harris, Irving, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Harris Program in Child Psychiatry, Child Development and Social Policy, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Harris Program, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Hartmann, Paul, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Infant care leave project, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - Infants in institutions, 1963-1981 (Box 2)
    - Inventories (Vol) Forms, Schedules, etc., 1962, 1973, undated (Box 2)
    - Israel trip: SP and AN's report, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Johnson & Johnson, 1976-1980 (Box 2)
    - Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Kirsten's Research, undated (Box 2)
    - Kriss, Marianne, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Kuhn, Mary, 1973-1981 (Box 2)
    - Landrum and Janis, undated (Box 2)
    - Landy, Gail, 1973-1986 (Box 2)
    - Lau, LaVay, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Lawrence, Teresa, 1980-1984 (Box 2)
    - Lead poisoning, 1965-1974 (Box 2)
    - Leonard, Martha, 1970, 1978-1983 (Box 2)
    - Levin, Vicki, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Dorothy (Research), 1974 (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Helen Block, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Ligimari, Joanne, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Lipman Papers, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Lipton, Rose C., 1964 (Box 2)
    - Lockwood Foundation, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Longitudinal Study in Child Development, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Longitudinal Study (Yale) Publications List, undated (Box 2)
    - Lourie, Reginald, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Lustman, Seymour, 1962-1970 (Box 2)
    - Lustman-Findling, Katharine, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - McDevitt, John B., 1977, 1981 (Box 2)
    - McKinnon, Rosemary, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - March of Dimes, 1978, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Marcus, Joseph, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Maternal and Child Health, Infant-Child Dev. Res. Center, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Maternal and Child Health block grant for handicapped children's services, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Mayes, Linda, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
    - Michael, Mary, 1981-1986 (Box 2)
    - Mika, Kirsten, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Minde, Klaus, 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Morrison, Bruce, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - Murphy, Lois, undated (Box 2)
    - Nachman, Patricia, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Nash, Samuel, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - National Association for the Education of Young Children, 1986 (Box 2)
    - National Association for the Education of Young Children Journal, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - National Committee for Adoption, 1986 (Box 2)
    - National Head Start Association Conference, 1989 (Box 2)
    - National Society for Autistic Children, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: promotion, 1979-1984 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: consulting editor, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: Mothers-PR900 Project--impressions at admission, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: Children in Families: Psychosocial Stress, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Day Care as a Family Support System,", undated (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Developmental Tasks and Developmental Needs Ages 2, 3, and 4,", Circa 1982 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Parenting in an Unresponsive Society,", Circa 1980 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Premature Mourning and Failure to Mourn,", 1986 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Problems of Behavior and Development Due to Environmental Stress,", 1978 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Supporting Family Life Through Child Care,", undated (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Social Casework,", 1964 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Working with Parents, Team Collaboration and Problem Solving,", 1970 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Group Care of Infants and Young Children,", 1970 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "A Child Development Research Project,", 1969 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Children in Changing Families,", 1979 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: award, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: CV and biographical., 1986, undated (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: notes and papers, 1981-1982, undated (Box 2)
    - Naylor, Audrey: "Teachers' Inventory of Emotional and Behavioral Development in Children Ages 2-6 Years,", 1977 (Box 2)
    - Ness, David, 1978-1982 (Box 2)
    - Parents' Magazine, 1981-1984, 1983-1990 (Box 3)
    - Patterson, June, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Patterson, June: criterion model, undated (Box 3)
    - Pawl, Jeree, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Prescriptions, copies of, Circa 1973-1976 (Box 3)
    - Psychiatry, 1981-1984 (Box 3)
    - Research protocols, 1970, 1977, n.d (Box 3)
    - Research protocols: child, 1977-1982 (Box 3)
    - Ritvo, S.: MK Memorial Lecture, undated (Box 3)
    - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, 1983 (Box 3)
    - St. Anthony Study (Infants in Institutions), Circa 1955-1963 (Box 3)
    - Senn, Milton J.E., 1972, undated (Box 3)
    - Shenker, Mrs. Patti, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Sheridan, Peggy, 1977, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Shonkoaff, Jack, 1981-1989 (Box 3)
    - Singer, Jerome and Dorothy, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Sparrow & Provence, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Sperry, Virginia, 1981-1983 (Box 3)
    - Sturner, Raymond A., 1977 (Box 3)
    - Topkis, Gladys, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Touching film, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Tourette's: extra copies, 1978, undated (Box 3)
    - World Congress on Infant Psychiatry, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Yale Child Study Center Inventories of Development: assessment instrument, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Yale Child Study Center Inventories of Development: copyright registration, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Yale Child Study Center Inventories of Development: NIMH Project proposal, undated (Box 3)
    - Yarrow, L. J., 1975-1976, undated (Box 3)
    - Yarrow manual, 1975, undated (Box 3)
    - To be sorted, 1978-1979, undated (Box 3)
    - Unidentified 16mm film (Box 3)
  - Writings
    - Discovery of the Body and Sense of Self from Infants in Institutions, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Notes on Infant Day Care, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Comments on Drs. Mahler and McDevitt's Paper…, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Early Recognition of Problems of Development to Mental Health…, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Young Children in Crises, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Some Determinants of Relevance of Stimuli in an Infant's Development, 1967 (Box 4)
    - The First Three Years, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Developmental History, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Comments on Infantile Disturbance and Later Development, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Contemporary Developments in Day Care, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Therapeutic Intervention: What Constitutes Intervention in the Early Years, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Some Issues in Day Care for Infants, Circa 1973 (Box 4)
    - The Mental Health Professions and the Preschool Child, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Diagnosis and Treatment of Preschool Children, 1974 (Box 4)
    - The Vulnerable Pre-School Child, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Clinical Assessment of the Development of Infants, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Remarks on Receiving the Aldrich Award, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Vulnerability and Mother-Child Interaction, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Application of Psychoanalytic Principles to Treatment and Prevention in Infancy, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Some Clinical Applications of Research on Parent-Child Relationships, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Influence of Early Environmental Factors on Learning, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Considerations in the Choice of Daycare, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Comments on Prevention and Treatment of Mental Health Problems in Infancy, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Notes on Some Common Developmental Problems of Infancy and Early Childhood, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Influence of Early Environmental Factors on Learning, 1977 (Box 4)
    - A Clinician's View of Affect Development in Infancy, 1978 (Box 4)
    - The Development of the Child--Birth to Three Years, 1979 (Box 4)
    - The Development of Parent-Child Relationships and the Psychological Parent, 1979 (Box 4)
    - The Development of Parent-Child Relationships and the Psychological Parent, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Changing Families and Child Rearing, 1979 (Box 4)
    - The Family: Structure and Support System, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Selected Comments on Coping in Young Children, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Development from Six to Twelve Months, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Organization of Developmental Findings and Classification of Developmental Disturbances, 1979 (Box 4)
    - The Problems of Vulnerability in Infancy: Clinical Examples and Theoretical Connections, 1979 (Box 4)
    - A Service-Centered Study: Methods of Intervention and Outcome, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Psychiatric Aspects of Child Day Care Programs, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Neuromotor, Speech and Psycho-Social Development in the First Three Years, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Infant Day Care: A View of Relationships between Theory and Practice, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Obstacles to Early Assessment and Treatment of Infants, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Common Indications of Psycho-Social Disorders of Infants and Young Children, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Family Relationships and Infant Mental Health Disorders, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Principles of Diagnosis of Mental Health Problems in Infancy, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Oral history, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Developmental Diagnosis: An Approach to Assessing Mental Health in Infants, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Dublin Paper: Developmental Diagnosis: An Approach to Assessing Mental Health in Infants, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Developmental Diagnosis: An Approach to Assessing Mental Health in Infants, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Struggling Against Deprivation and Trauma, 1982 (Box 4)
    - The Yale Child Welfare Research Program: Description and Results, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Roundtable on Development in the Early Years: Some Practical Applications of Clinical and Research Data, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Some Developmental Assessment and Treatment of Infants and Young Children, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Working with Disadvantaged Parents and Their Children, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Philadelphia Paper--Early Deficits, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Early Deficits, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Theoretical Concepts and Clinical Perspectives, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Diagnosis of Child Abuse - Pediatric Perspectives, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Moore-Fine Compendium: "On Maturation,", 1983 (Box 4)
    - Working with Disadvantaged Parents and Their Children: Costs and Benefits, 1983 (Box 4)
    - The Yale Child Welfare Research Program, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Development in the Early Years: Some Practical Applications of Clinical and Research Data, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Some Reflections on the Relevance of Service-Centered Research for Infant Mental Health, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Workshop on Developmental and Behavioral Assessment of the Newborn and Young Child, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Some Relationships Between Education and Psychotherapy in the Treatment of Infants and Toddlers (Institute for Psychoanalysis Paper, Chicago), 1984 (Box 5)
    - Some Relationships Between Education and Psychotherapy in the Treatment of Infants and Toddlers (Institute for Psychoanalysis Paper, Chicago), 1984 (Box 5)
    - The Contribution of a Sibling to the Development of an Atypical Child, 1985 (Box 5)
    - On the Efficacy of Early Intervention Programs, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Early Child Development, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Psychiatric Aspects of Child Day Care Programs, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Articles from Parents Magazine, 1981-1985 (Box 5)
    - Clinical and Multivariate Approaches to the Nosology of Pervasive Developmental Disorders, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Summary from The Feeling Child, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Caring for Infants and Toddlers in a Changing Society, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Disorders of Atypical Development: Diagnostic Issues Raised by a Spectrum Disorder in Handbook of Autism and Pervasive Developmental Disorders, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Disorders of Atypical Development: Diagnostic Issues Raised by a Spectrum Disorder in Handbook of Autism and Pervasive Developmental Disorders, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Remarks at My Retirement Dinner, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Some Thoughts about Approaches to the Vulnerable Child Then and Now, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Psychoanalytic Views of Separation in Infancy and Early Childhood, 1987 (Box 5)
    - A Developmental Pediatrician's Experience with Four Year Olds in School, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Influencing and Interrupting Cycles of Maladaptation, 1987 (Box 5)
    - "What's Happening to Infants and Toddlers Today?,", 1988 (Box 5)
    - Resolved: Day Care is the Best Care for Children under Age Five of Working Americans (Debate Forum), 1988 (Box 5)
    - Transitional and Solacing Objects of the Early Years, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Diagnosis and Classification in Infancy and Early Childhood, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Infancy and Early Childhood in Psychological Development: From Health to Illness, a chapter in Pediatrics, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Developmental Assessment, undated (Box 5)
    - Developmental Appraisal, undated (Box 5)
    - Developing Treatment Modalities for Children Who Have Experienced Early Deprivation, undated (Box 5)
    - Depression in the Earliest Years, undated (Box 5)
    - Depression in Infancy?, undated (Box 5)
    - Danger Signals in Development, undated (Box 5)
    - An Interview for One Day, undated (Box 5)
    - Disturbances in Mother-Infant Relationships During the First Year of Life, undated (Box 5)
    - Some Thoughts about Organization of Diagnostic Data, undated (Box 5)
    - Some Suggested Questions for Eliciting Developmental Data, undated (Box 5)
    - Research on Infancy of Special Relevance for Mental Health, undated (Box 5)
    - Common Indications of Psycho-Social Disorders of Infants and Young Children, undated (Box 5)
    - Developmental Diagnosis: An Approach to Assessing Mental Health in Infants, undated (Box 5)
    - Developmental Assessment and Its Implications for Individualized Treatment Plans for Atypical and Autistic Children, undated (Box 5)
    - Failure to Thrive Paper, undated (Box 5)
    - Comments on Developmental Phase and Psychosomatic Symptoms, undated (Box 5)
    - The Development of the Child - Birth to Three Years, undated (Box 5)
    - Notes on Childhood Psychosis, undated (Box 5)
    - Behavior Indicators of Mother-Infant Relationship, undated (Box 5)
    - Ego Development of the Blind Child, undated (Box 5)
    - Selected Comments on Coping in Young Children, undated (Box 5)
    - Sensory Deprivation in Infancy, undated (Box 5)
    - Some Psychoanalytic Perspectives on Separation in Early Childhood, undated (Box 5)
    - Some Relations of Constitution, Environment, and Personality as Observed in a Longitudinal Study of Child Development, undated (Box 5)
    - On Predicting Development, undated (Box 5)
    - Family Relationships and Infant Mental Health Disorders, undated (Box 5)
    - Development of Children with Lead Poisoning, undated (Box 5)
    - Days of Toddlers: Observations & Reflections on Toddler Interaction (3 copies in black binders), undated (Box 6)
    - Loose drafts, typescripts, outlines, notes, and fragments, undated (Box 6)
  - Personal Papers
    - Award: C. Anderson Aldrich, 1977 (Box 6)
    - American Academy of Child Psychiatry, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Continuing education, 1977-1984 (Box 6)
    - Directions - SP's home, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Emeritus, 1987 (Box 6)
    - Fringe benefits, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Insurance, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Watch guarantee, 1981 (Box 6)
    - OPS (Office of Professional Services) billing, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Provence, S. - Y-NHH, 1986 (Box 6)
    - Cur. Vitae Introduction statements, 1969, 1984-1988 (Box 6)
    - Triennial leave, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Parking, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
    - Sabbatical, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Trails, undated (Box 6)
    - Transition, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Licenses, 1977-1991 (Box 6)
    - Narcotics licenses, 1972-1991 (Box 6)
    - Directions-Hunting Ridge Farms Rd., undated (Box 6)
    - Personnel Activity Report, undated (Box 6)
    - Challenge of Daycare: book reviews, etc., 1977-1979 (Box 6)
- Additional material, 1953-1987; Accession 1997-M-035
  - Writings, 1953-1957, 1961-1969, 1971-1977, 1981-1987, undated (Box 1)
- Additional material, Circa 1965-1985; Accession 2000-M-107
  Conditions Governing Access
  Research data and patient case files contain personal and senstitive information and are closed until January 1, 2086.
  Consists of longitudinal studies, day care studies, patient case files, CWR study data, and topical files [includes some film]. Includes correspondence and topical files related to the National Center for Clinical Infant Programs, on whose board Provence served.
  - Longitudinal study[?] (Box 1)
    Research data contains personal and sensitive information and are closed until January 1, 2086.
  - Day care study (Box 7–15)
  - National Center for Clinical Infant Programs (Box 16–17)
  - CWR study data (Box 18–19)
  - Child Development Unit records (Box 20)
  - Services for children with special needs [assessment data] (Box 21)
  - Patient case files, correspondence, photographs (Box 22–24)
    Patient case files contain personal and sensitive information and are closed until January 1, 2086.
  - Miscellaneous files relating to longitudinal study, day care study, foster parents litigation [includes film from the day care study] (Box 25)